(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I am a papercutter.
أنا أقطع الورق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I cut stories.
أقطعه للقصص
So my process is very straightforward.
عملي بسيط جدا
I take a piece of paper,
ألتقط ورقة
I visualize my story,
وأتخيل قصتي
sometimes I sketch, sometimes I don't.
أحيانا أرسمها أو لا أفعل
And as my image
وبما أن صورة قصتي
is already inside the paper,
موجودة في الورقة
I just have to remove
ما علي إلا أن أزيل
what's not from that story.
ما ليس من القصة
So I didn't come to papercutting
لم أصل إلى تقطيع الورق
in a straight line.
بالسير في خط مستقيم
In fact,
في الواقع
I see it more as a spiral.
أظنه حلزونيا
I was not born
لم أولد
with a blade in my hand.
بنصل في يدي
And I don't remember papercutting as a child.
ولا أذكر أني كنت أقطع الورق في طفولتي
As a teenager,
وفي المراهقة
I was sketching, drawing,
كنت أصمم وأرسم
and I wanted to be an artist.
وأردت أن أصبح فنانة
But I was also a rebel.
ولكني أيضا كنت متمردة
And I left everything
وتركت كل شيء
and went for a long series of odd jobs.
وعملت في عدة وظائف غريبة
So among them,
فمثلاً
I have been a shepherdess,
عملت كراعية غنم
a truck driver,
سائقة شاحنة
a factory worker,
عاملة في مصنع
a cleaning lady.
عاملة نظافة
I worked in tourism for one year
وعملت بالسياحة لمدة عام
in Mexico,
بالمكسيك
one year in Egypt.
ولمدة عام بمصر
I moved for two years
عشت لعامين
in Taiwan.
في تايوان
And then I settled in New York
واستقريت في نيويورك
where I became a tour guide.
حيث عملت كمرشدة سياحية
And I still worked as a tour leader,
وظللت هكذا
traveled back and forth
أتنقل من بلد لآخر
in China, Tibet and Central Asia.
الصين والتبت وآسيا الوسطى
So of course, it took time, and I was nearly 40,
استغرق ذلك زمنا، وقاربت على الأربعين
and I decided it's time
وقررت أن الوقت حان
to start as an artist.
لأبدأ طريقي كفنانة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I chose papercutting
اخترت تقطيع الورق
because paper is cheap,
فالورق رخيص
it's light,
وخفيف
and you can use it
ويمكنك استخدامه
in a lot of different ways.
بطرق شتى
And I chose the language of silhouette
واخترت مجال السيلويت
because graphically it's very efficient.
لأنه مؤثر من ناحية الجرافيك
And it's also just getting to the essential of things.
ومباشر وبسيط
So the word "silhouette"
وكلمة "سيلويت"
comes from a minister of finance,
من اسم وزير المالية
Etienne de Silhouette.
إيتين دي سيلويت
And he slashed so many budgets
الذي خفض الميزانية
that people said they couldn't afford
مما منع الناس من تحمل نفقة
paintings anymore,
اللوحات الملونة
and they needed to have their portrait
فاضطروا إلى الحصول على بورتريهات
"a la silhouette."
"على طريقة سيلويت"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I made series of images, cuttings,
صممت سلسلة من الصور وقطعتها
and I assembled them in portfolios.
وجمعتها في ملفات
And people told me --
وعلق الناس على أعمالي
like these 36 views of the Empire State building --
كهذا المشهد السريالي لمبنى "إمباير ستيت"
they told me, "You're making artist books."
"أنت تصنعين كتبًا فنية."
So artist books have a lot of definitions.
فالكتب الفنية لها عدة تعريفات
They come in a lot of different shapes.
وأشكال مختلفة
But to me,
وأنا أرى أنها
they are fascinating objects
تجمع أشكال مدهشة
to visually narrate a story.
تروي القصة من خلالها
They can be with words
وقد تصاحبها الكلمات
or without words.
أو لا
And I have a passion
وأنا لدي شغف
for images and for words.
بالصور والكلمات
I love pun
أحب التورية
and the relation to the unconscious.
والعلاقة بالعقل الباطن
I love oddities of languages.
وغرائب اللغات
And everywhere I lived, I learned the languages,
وفي كل مكان عشت به تعلمت لغته
but never mastered them.
لكني لم أتقن أي منها
So I'm always looking
لذا دائمًا أبحث
for the false cognates
عن المترادفات الزائفة
or identical words in different languages.
أو الكلمات المتطابقة في لغتين
So as you can guess, my mother tongue is French.
ومن حديثي تعرفون أن لغتي الأولى الفرنسية
And my daily language is English.
ولغة الحديث اليومي الإنجليزية
So I did a series of work
فقمت بتنفيذ سلسلة أعمال
where it was identical words
من الكلمات المتطابقة
in French and in English.
في الفرنسية والإنجليزية
So one of these works
وأحدها
is the "Spelling Spider."
هو "عنكبوت الهجاء"
So the Spelling Spider
وعنكبوت الهجاء
is a cousin of the spelling bee.
هو ابن عم نحلة الهجاء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it's much more connected to the Web.
لكنه يرتبط أكثر بالشبكة العنكبوتية
And this spider
وهذا العنكبوت
spins a bilingual alphabet.
ينسج أبجدية بلغتين
So you can read "architecture active"
فيمكنك أن تقرأ "architecture active"
or "active architecture."
أو "active architecture"
So this spider goes through the whole alphabet
ويمر العنكبوت بالأبجدية كلها
with identical adjectives and substantives.
مع كافة الصفات والأسماء المتطابقة
So if you don't know one of these languages,
فإن لم تكن تعلم إحدى اللغتين
it's instant learning.
يمكنك تعلمها فورًا
And one ancient form of the book
وإحدى صيغ الكتاب القديمة
is scrolls.
هي القوائم
So scrolls are very convenient,
وهي سهلة جدًا
because you can create a large image
فيمكنك صنع صورة كبيرة
on a very small table.
على منضدة صغيرة جدًا
So the unexpected consequences of that
وقد لا تتوقعه
is that you only see one part of your image,
أنك ترى جزءًا واحدًا فقط من صورتك
so it makes a very freestyle architecture.
إلا أنه أسلوب حر في الفن المعماري
And I'm making all those kinds of windows.
وأقوم بصنع كل هذه النوافذ
So it's to look beyond the surface.
لننظر عميقًا
It's to have a look
لنتأمل في
at different worlds.
عوالم مختلفة
And very often I've been an outsider.
كنت معظم الوقت مغتربة
So I want to see how things work
لذا أرغب في معرفة كيفية عمل الأشياء
and what's happening.
وماذا يحدث
So each window
كل نافذة
is an image
هي صورة
and is a world
وعالم
that I often revisit.
زرته كثيرًا
And I revisit this world
وأعاود زيارته
thinking about the image
وأنا أفكر في الصورة
or cliché about what we want to do,
أو أصيغ ما أرغب في تنفيذه
and what are the words, colloquialisms,
وأبحث عن الكلمات والألفاظ العامية
that we have with the expressions.
التي نستخدمها مع كل تعبير
It's all if.
وكلها افتراضات
So what if we were living in balloon houses?
فماذا لو كنا نعيش في منازل بالونية؟
It would make a very uplifting world.
سيرتفع العالم
And we would leave a very low footprint on the planet.
وسيقل التلوث على الكوكب
It would be so light.
وسيصبح أكثر خفة
So sometimes I view from the inside,
لذا أحيانًا ما أتأمل من الداخل
like EgoCentriCity
بأنانية
and the inner circles.
وأنظر للدوائر الداخلية
Sometimes it's a global view,
وأحيانًا ما أتأمل في الصورة العالمية
to see our common roots
لأصل لجذورنا المشتركة
and how we can use them to catch dreams.
وكيف يمكننا استغلالها لنحقق أحلامنا
And we can use them also
كما يمكننا استخدامها
as a safety net.
كشبكة وقاية
And my inspirations
إلهامي
are very eclectic.
شديد الانتقائية
I'm influenced by everything I read,
وأتأثر بكل ما أقرأ
everything I see.
وأشاهد
I have some stories that are humorous,
لدي بعض القصص الفكاهية
like "Dead Beats."
مثل "الضربات المميتة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Other ones are historical.
وأخرى تاريخية
Here it's "CandyCity."
مثل "مدينة الحلوى"
It's a non-sugar-coated
وهو تاريخ السكر
history of sugar.
بدون إضافة سكر
It goes from slave trade
بدءًا من تجارة الرق
to over-consumption of sugar
وحتى زيادة استهلاك السكر
with some sweet moments in between.
ولحظات رائعة بين الحدثين
And sometimes I have an emotional response to news,
أحيانًا أشعر بتفاعل عاطفي مع الأخبار
such as the 2010 Haitian earthquake.
مثل زلزال هايتي 2010
Other times, it's not even my stories.
وأحيانًا لا أنسج قصصي
People tell me their lives,
لكن الآخرين يخبروني عن حياتهم
their memories, their aspirations,
ذكرياتهم وطموحاتهم
and I create a mindscape.
فأخلق تصورًا شاملاً
I channel their history
وأوجه تاريخهم
[so that] they have a place to go back
ليجدوا مكانًا يعودوا إليه
to look at their life and its possibilities.
ويتأملوا حياتهم بكل احتمالاتها
I call them Freudian cities.
أطلق عليها مدن فرويد
I cannot speak for all my images,
لا يمكنني الحديث عن كل صوري
so I'll just go through a few of my worlds
سأمر سريعًا على بعض من عوالمي
just with the title.
وعناوينها
"ModiCity."
مدينة الأشياء الصغيرة
"ElectriCity."
مدينة الكهرباء
"MAD Growth on Columbus Circle."
النمو المدهش في دائرة كولومبس
"ReefCity."
مدينة الشراع
"A Web of Time."
شبكة الزمن
"Chaos City."
مدينة الفوضى
"Daily Battles."
معارك يومية
"FeliCity."
مدينة البهجة
"Floating Islands."
جزر عائمة
And at one point,
وذات مرة
I had to do "The Whole Nine Yards."
قمت بعمل "9 ياردات كاملة"
So it's actually a papercut that's nine yards long.
وهو عمل طوله تسع ياردات بالفعل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So in life and in papercutting,
في الحياة وتقطيع الورق
everything is connected.
كل شيء متصل
One story leads to another.
وقصة تقود إلى أخرى
I was also interested
كنت مهتمة أيضًا
in the physicality of this format,
بطبيعة هذا الشكل
because you have to walk to see it.
فعليك أن تمشي لتشاهده
And parallel to my cutting
وهكذا يتوازى تقطيع الورق
is my running.
مع الجري
I started with small images,
بدأت بصور صغيرة
I started with a few miles.
بأميال قليلة
Larger images, I started to run marathons.
ومع الصور الأكبر بدأت في الماراثون
Then I went to run 50K, then 60K.
ثم جريت لـ 50 كجم ثم 60 كجم
Then I ran 50 miles -- ultramarathons.
ثم جريت لـ 50 ميل، ماراثون المسافات البعيدة
And I still feel I'm running,
ولازلت أشعر أني أجري
it's just the training
مجرد تدريب
to become a long-distance papercutter.
لأصبح مقطعة ورق للمسافات الطويلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And running gives me a lot of energy.
والجري يمدني بالطاقة
Here is a three-week papercutting marathon
وها هو ماراثون لثلاثة أسابيع من العمل
at the Museum of Arts and Design
في متحف "آرتس أند ديزاين"
in New York City.
في مدينة نيويورك
The result is "Hells and Heavens."
النتيجة هي "جحيم ونعيم"
It's two panels 13 ft. high.
وهي للوحتين بطول 13 قدم
They were installed in the museum on two floors,
تم تثبيتهما في المتحف في دورين
but in fact, it's a continuous image.
لكنها في الحقيقة صورة متصلة
And I call it "Hells and Heavens"
سميتها "جحيم ونعيم"
because it's daily hells and daily heavens.
فهي جحيم ونعيم يومي
There is no border in between.
ولا حد بينهما
Some people are born in hells,
بعض الناس ولدوا في جحيم
and against all odds, they make it to heavens.
ورغم كل الصعاب وصلوا إلى الجنة
Other people make the opposite trip.
وآخرين ساروا في الطريق المعاكس
That's the border.
وهذا هو الحد
You have sweatshops in hells.
هناك متاجر حلوى في الجحيم
You have people renting their wings in the heavens.
ومن يؤجرون أجنحتهم في الجنة
And then you have all those individual stories
وكل القصص الفردية
where sometimes we even have the same action,
التي قد يتم فيها الأحداث نفسها
and the result puts you in hells or in heavens.
والنتيجة تضعك في الجحيم أو النعيم
So the whole "Hells and Heavens"
فعمل "جحيم ونعيم"
is about free will
يدور حول حرية الإرداة
and determinism.
والحتمية
And in papercutting,
وبالنسبة لتقطيع الورق
you have the drawing as the structure itself.
يكون الرسم هو نفسه الهيكل
So you can take it off the wall.
ويمكنك خلعه عن الحائط
Here it's an artist book installation
ها هو كتاب فني
called "Identity Project."
يسمى "مشروع الهوية."
It's not autobiographical identities.
ولا يعني ذلك الهوية الذاتية
They are more our social identities.
وإنما الهوية الاجتماعية
And then you can just walk behind them
ويمكنك السير خلفها
and try them on.
وتجربة لبسها
So it's like the different layers
فهي أشبه بالطبقات المختلفة
of what we are made of
لما يشكل شخصياتنا
and what we present to the world
وما نقدمه للعالم
as an identity.
كهوية
That's another artist book project.
وها هو مشروع كتاب آخر
In fact, in the picture, you have two of them.
في الواقع هذه الصورة تشمل اثنين
It's one I'm wearing
واحد أرتديه
and one that's on exhibition
وآخر في المعرض
at the Center for Books Arts in New York City.
بمركز فنون الكتاب في نيويورك
Why do I call it a book?
لم أسميه كتابًا؟
It's called "Fashion Statement,"
عنوانه "بيان الموضة"
and there are quotes about fashion,
ويشمل مقولات حول الموضة
so you can read it,
يمكنك قراءتها
and also,
وأيضًا لأن
because the definition of artist book
تعريف الكتاب الفني
is very generous.
مطاط جدًا
So artist books, you take them off the wall.
فيمكنك رفع الكتب الفنية من على الحائط
You take them for a walk.
أو اصطحابها معك أثناء السير
You can also install them as public art.
أو تعليقها كعمل فني يطلع عليه الجمهور
Here it's in Scottsdale, Arizona,
هذا في سكوتسدايل بالأريزونا
and it's called "Floating Memories."
واسمها "ذكريات هائمة"
So it's regional memories,
وهي ذكريات تتعلق بالمكان
and they are just randomly moved by the wind.
تحركها الرياح بعشوائية
I love public art.
أحب الفن الشعبي
And I entered competitions
وخضت مسابقات
for a long time.
طويلة المدى
After eight years of rejection,
وبعد ثماني سنوات
I was thrilled to get my first commission
سعدت لتفويضي بأول مهمة
with the Percent for Art in New York City.
مع "بيرسنت فور أرت" في نيويورك
It was for a merger station
كان لمحطة عمل
for emergency workers and firemen.
خاصة بعمال الطوارئ ورجال الإطفاء
I made an artist book
صنعت كتاب فني
that's in stainless steel
بالحديد المقاوم للصدأ
instead of paper.
بدلا من الورق
I called it "Working in the Same Direction."
أسميته "العمل في نفس الاتجاه"
But I added weathervanes on both sides
لكني أضفت دوارات رياح على الجانبين
to show that they cover all directions.
لأوضح أنه يغطي كافة الاتجاهات
With public art,
وفي الفن الشعبي
I could also make cut glass.
يمكنني أيضًا أن أقطع الزجاج
Here it's faceted glass in the Bronx.
وها هي أوجه من الزجاج في برونكس
And each time I make public art,
وفي كل مرة أصنع عملاً فنيًا شعبيًا
I want something that's really relevant
أريد عملاً يرتبط
to the place it's installed.
بالمكان الذي سيوضع به
So for the subway in New York,
ففي المترو بنيويورك
I saw a correspondence
وجدت ترابطًا
between riding the subway
بين ركوب المترو
and reading.
والقراءة
It is travel in time, travel on time.
سفر في الزمان وسفر الزمان
And Bronx literature,
وأدب برونكس
it's all about Bronx writers
معظمه عن أدباء برونكس
and their stories.
وقصصهم
Another glass project
وهذا مشروع آخر من الزجاج
is in a public library
في مكتبة عامة
in San Jose, California.
في سان جوز بكاليفورنيا
So I made a vegetable point of view
وكانت لي نظرة متحيزة للخضروات
of the growth of San Jose.
ربطتها بسان جوز
So I started in the center
فبدأت من المركز
with the acorn
بالبلوط
for the Ohlone Indian civilization.
لحضارة أولون الهندية
Then I have the fruit from Europe
ثم أضفت الفاكهة من أوروبا
for the ranchers.
لأصحاب المزارع
And then the fruit of the world for Silicon Valley today.
ثم فاكهة من حول العالم لقرية سيليكون
And it's still growing.
ولازالت تنمو
So the technique, it's cut,
التقنية المستخدمة هي القطع
sandblasted, etched
والتفريغ والحفر
and printed glass into architectural glass.
والزجاج المطبوع على الزجاج المقطع
And outside the library,
وخارج المكتبة
I wanted to make a place to cultivate your mind.
أردت أن أقيم مكانًا لإثارة العقول
I took library material
فأخرجت مواد المكتبة
that had fruit in their title
التي تتضمن عناوينها أسماء فاكهة
and I used them to make an orchard walk
وصنعت ممر بستاني
with these fruits of knowledge.
بفاكهة المعرفة
I also planted the bibliotree.
فزرعت شجرة الكتب
So it's a tree,
وهي شجرة
and in its trunk you have the roots of languages.
ومن جذعها تخرج جذور اللغة
And it's all about international writing systems.
وهي عن نظم الكتابة العالمية
And on the branches
وعلى الأفرع
you have library material growing.
تنمو مواد المكتبة
You can also have function and form
ويمكنك الحصول على الفعالية والشكل الخارجي
with public art.
من خلال الفن الشعبي
So in Aurora, Colorado it's a bench.
ففي أورورا بكولورادو يوجد مقعد
But you have a bonus with this bench.
لكن هذا المقعد به ميزة
Because if you sit a long time in summer in shorts,
فإذا جلست عليه طويلاً في الصيف مرتديًا الشورت
you will walk away
ستمشي
with temporary branding of
بعلامات مؤقتة
the story element on your thighs.
من رسومات القصة على فخذيك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another functional work,
ومن الأعمال الأخرى الفعالة
it's in the south side of Chicago
في جنوب شيكاغو
for a subway station.
لمحطة أنفاق
And it's called "Seeds of the Future are Planted Today."
بعنوان "بذور المستقبل تزرع اليوم"
It's a story about transformation
وهي قصة عن التبادل
and connections.
والاتصالات
So it acts as a screen
وهي تعمل كشاشة
to protect the rail and the commuter,
لحماية السكة الحديدية والمسافر
and not to have objects falling on the rails.
ومنع الأشياء من السقوط على القضبان
To be able to change fences
وتحويل الأسيجة
and window guards into flowers,
والنوافذ أيضًا إلى زهور
it's fantastic.
أمر رائع
And here I've been working for the last three years
وعملت على ذلك منذ 3 سنوات
with a South Bronx developer
مع مطور من جنوب برونكس
to bring art to life
لنقل الفن إلى الحياة
to low-income buildings
وتقليل تكاليف المباني
and affordable housing.
والمنازل
So each building has its own personality.
وليكن لكل منزل هويته الخاصة
And sometimes it's about a legacy of the neighborhood,
وأحيانًا يتعلق الرسم بتراث الحي
like in Morrisania, about the jazz history.
كتاريخ موسيقى الجاز في موريزانيا
And for other projects, like in Paris,
ومشاريع أخرى، كمشروع باريس
it's about the name of the street.
عن اسم الشارع
It's called Rue des Prairies -- Prairie Street.
واسمه شارع المرج
So I brought back the rabbit,
لذا أحضرت الأرنب
the dragonfly,
واليعسوب
to stay in that street.
ليظلوا بالشارع
And in 2009,
وفي 2009
I was asked to make a poster
طلب مني صنع بوستر
to be placed in the subway cars in New York City
ليوضع في نفق السيارات بنيويورك
for a year.
لمدة عام
So that was a very captive audience.
كان جمهورًا حبيسًا
And I wanted to give them an escape.
وأردت أن أجعل له مهربًا
I created "All Around Town."
صنعت "حول المدينة"
It is a papercutting,
من خلال تقطيع الورق
and then after, I added color on the computer.
ثم إضافة اللون بواسطة الكمبيوتر
So I can call it techno-crafted.
يمكنني أن أسميه "تكنو-كرافت"
And along the way,
وخلال عملي
I'm kind of making papercuttings
أقوم بتقطيع الورق
and adding other techniques.
وإضافة التقنيات الأخرى
But the result is always to have stories.
والنتيجة دائمًا هي القصص
So the stories, they have a lot of possibilities.
وللقصص احتمالات عديدة
They have a lot of scenarios.
وسيناريوهات مختلفة
I don't know the stories.
لا أعرفها كلها
I take images from our global imagination,
لكني أستوحي الصور من خيال العالم
from cliché, from things we are thinking about,
من الكليشيه والأشياء التي نفكر بها
from history.
من التاريخ
And everybody's a narrator,
وكل شخص هو راوي
because everybody has a story to tell.
لأن كل شخص لديه قصة ليرويها
But more important
لكن الأهم
is everybody has to make a story
أن يصنع كل منا قصته
to make sense of the world.
ليصبح لهذا العالم معنى
And in all these universes,
وفي كل هذه الأكوان
it's like imagination is the vehicle
الخيال مركبة
to be transported with,
تنقلنا
but the destination is our minds
والوجهة هي عقولنا
and how we can reconnect
وكيفية إعادة التواصل
with the essential and with the magic.
مع الأفكار المبهمة والسحر
And it's what story cutting is all about.
وهو ما يدور حوله فن تقطيع الورق
(Applause)
(تصفيق)